What are the advantages of having seniority at work?
Using a seniority structure in the workplace can have benefits for both employees and companies. Some of the advantages include:
Employee loyalty
Employees who understand the seniority policy of their companies may be more likely to stay with one organization for a longer period of time rather than switch companies. If they understand the seniority and reward structure based on years of service, they may find that they can get more benefits from being patient than continuously job hunting. This can create less turnover within a company, making it easier to set and achieve efficiency and productivity goals.
Overtime
In certain professions, employees with the most seniority may have the first option to request or sign up for overtime shifts. Overtime in most occupations usually comes with additional pay scales, making it an enticing option for people who want to make more money.
Job security
Having more seniority in the workplace may lead to better job security. In situations of staff downsizing and layoffs, companies may choose to keep employees with the most seniority to be objective about deciding who gets to keep their positions. Though every organization differs, working for a company for an extended period may result in you maintaining employment through adverse scenarios.
Paid time off
Employees with high seniority levels may have the opportunity to receive more paid time off. For some companies, more seniority means more paid vacation, sick days and personal days per year. Increases in paid time off commonly come in three- or five-year increments of service.
Promotions
Employees with more seniority may have a better likelihood of receiving a promotion than their coworkers. When management members look to promote internally, they may use seniority as a prerequisite for choosing candidates.
Preferred jobs
Those with more seniority may be able to choose the jobs they do within their company. In industries like plumbing, construction or electrical work, contractors or labourers with the most seniority may have the choice of which job sites to work at or which calls to take. This may be beneficial for both the employee and the company since the best skills get assigned to the most desired jobs with improved performance as a result.
Predictability
Depending on the seniority structure at your company, you may be able to predict when you will receive benefits for your years of service. For union-represented industries, a governing board sets the pay and vacation day increase schedule for an entire company or union. Knowing when you will receive more perks may make it more enticing to stay with a company to reach certain milestones.
Training opportunities
Employees with more seniority may have more options to attend special training sessions than other members of the organization. They also may have the chance to take part in continuing education or training programs funded by the company. This may help employees with seniority prepare to advance their careers even further.
Salary or wages
Employees with more seniority may earn more than entry-level employees. Some companies may give guaranteed wage increases after reaching seniority milestones. Other organizations may offer the possibility of salary increases after a certain period.
Additional perks
Some companies with seniority policies may offer other types of incentives as employees progress through their time with the company. Options such as office or cubicle location, preferred parking stall, choice of technology or discounts for certain services may be offered to more senior staff, helping make employees' lives easier.






FUNCTIONS OF MANAGEMENT
Management has been described as a social process involving responsibility for economical and effective planning & regulation of the operation of an enterprise in the fulfillment of given purposes.
It is a dynamic process consisting of various elements and activities. These activities are different from operative functions like marketing, finance, purchase etc. Rather these activities are common to each and every manger irrespective of his level or status.
But the most widely accepted are functions of management given by KOONTZ and O'DONNEL i.e. Planning, Organizing, Staffing, Directing and Controlling.
For theoretical purposes, it may be convenient to separate the function of management but practically these functions are overlapping in nature i.e. they are highly inseparable. Each function blends into the other & each affects the performance of others.
Different experts have classified functions of management.
According to George & Jerry, "There are four fundamental functions of management i.e. planning, organizing, actuating and controlling".
According to Henry Fayol, "To manage is to forecast and plan, to organize, to command, & to control".
Whereas Luther Gullick has given a keyword 'POSDCORB' where P stands for Planning, O for Organizing, S for Staffing, D for Directing, Co for Co-ordination, R for reporting & B for Budgeting.
Steps in Planning Function
Establishment of objectives 
Planning requires a systematic approach.
Planning starts with the setting of goals and objectives to be achieved.
Objectives provide a rationale for undertaking various activities as well as indicate direction of efforts.
Moreover objectives focus the attention of managers on the end results to be achieved.
As a matter of fact, objectives provide nucleus to the planning process. Therefore, objectives should be stated in a clear, precise and unambiguous language. Otherwise the activities undertaken are bound to be ineffective.
As far as possible, objectives should be stated in quantitative terms. For example, Number of men working, wages given, units produced, etc. But such an objective cannot be stated in quantitative terms like performance of quality control manager, effectiveness of personnel manager.
Such goals should be specified in qualitative terms.
Hence objectives should be practical, acceptable, workable and achievable.

According to Koontz & O'Donell, "Planning is deciding in advance what to do, how to do and who is to do it. Planning bridges the gap between where we are to, where we want to go. It makes possible things to occur which would not otherwise occur"
Planning Function of Management
Planning means looking ahead and chalking out future courses of action to be followed. It is a preparatory step. It is a systematic activity which determines when, how and who is going to perform a specific job. Planning is a detailed programme regarding future courses of action.
It is rightly said "Well plan is half done". Therefore planning takes into consideration available & prospective human and physical resources of the organization so as to get effective co-ordination, contribution & perfect adjustment. It is the basic management function which includes formulation of one or more detailed plans to achieve optimum balance of needs or demands with the available resources.
1. Establishment of Planning Premises
Planning premises are the assumptions about the lively shape of events in future.
They serve as a basis of planning.
Establishment of planning premises is concerned with determining where one tends to deviate from the actual plans and causes of such deviations.
It is to find out what obstacles are there in the way of business during the course of operations.
Establishment of planning premises is concerned to take such steps that avoids these obstacles to a great extent.
Planning premises may be internal or external. Internal includes capital investment policy, management labour relations, philosophy of management, etc. Whereas external includes socio-economic, political and economical changes.
Internal premises are controllable whereas external are non-controllable.
1. Choice of alternative course of action
When forecast are available and premises are established, a number of alternative course of actions have to be considered.
For this purpose, each and every alternative will be evaluated by weighing its pros and cons in the light of resources available and requirements of the organization.
The merits, demerits as well as the consequences of each alternative must be examined before the choice is being made.
After objective and scientific evaluation, the best alternative is chosen.
The planners should take help of various quantitative techniques to judge the stability of an alternative.
CHARACTERISTICS OF PLANNING
Planning is goal-oriented. 
Planning is made to achieve desired objective of business.
The goals established should general acceptance otherwise individual efforts & energies will go misguided and misdirected.
Planning identifies the action that would lead to desired goals quickly & economically.
It provides sense of direction to various activities. E.g. Maruti Udhyog is trying to capture once again Indian Car Market by launching diesel models.
Planning is looking ahead. 
Planning is done for future.
It requires peeping in future, analyzing it and predicting it.
Thus planning is based on forecasting.
A plan is a synthesis of forecast.
It is a mental predisposition for things to happen in future.
Planning is the primary function of management/Primacy of Planning. 
Planning lays foundation for other functions of management.
It serves as a guide for organizing, staffing, directing and controlling.
All the functions of management are performed within the framework of plans laid out.
Therefore planning is the basic or fundamental function of management.
Planning is a Continuous Process. 
Planning is a never ending function due to the dynamic business environment.
Plans are also prepared for specific period f time and at the end of that period, plans are subjected to revaluation and review in the light of new requirements and changing conditions.
Planning never comes into end till the enterprise exists issues, problems may keep cropping up and they have to be tackled by planning effectively.
ORGANIZING FUNCTION OF MANAGEMENT
Organizing is the function of management which follows planning.
It is a function in which the synchronization and combination of human, physical and financial resources takes place. All the three resources are important to get results. Therefore, organizational function helps in achievement of results which in fact is important for the functioning of a concern.
According to Chester Barnard, "Organizing is a function by which the concern is able to define the role positions, the jobs related and the co-ordination between authority and responsibility". Hence, a manager always has to organize in order to get results.
A manager performs organizing function with the help of following steps:-
Identification of activities - All the activities which have to be performed in a concern have to be identified first. For example, preparation of accounts, making sales, record keeping, quality control, inventory control, etc. All these activities have to be grouped and classified into units.
Departmentally organizing the activities - In this step, the manager tries to combine and group similar and related activities into units or departments. This organization of dividing the whole concern into independent units and departments is called departmentation.
Classifying the authority - Once the departments are made, the manager likes to classify the powers and its extent to the managers. This activity of giving a rank in order to the managerial positions is called hierarchy.
The top management is into formulation of policies, the middle level management into departmental supervision and lower level management into supervision of foremen.
The clarification of authority help in bringing efficiency in the running of a concern. This helps in achieving efficiency in the running of a concern. This helps in avoiding wastage of time, money, effort, in avoidance of duplication or overlapping of efforts and this helps in bringing smoothness in a concern's working.
Co-ordination between authority and responsibility - Relationships are established among various groups to enable smooth interaction toward the achievement of the organizational goal. Each individual is made aware of his authority and he/she knows whom they have to take orders from and to whom they are accountable and to whom they have to report. A clear organizational structure is drawn and all the employees are made aware of it.
Staffing Function of Management
The managerial function of staffing involves manning the organization structure through proper and effective selection, appraisal and development of the personnels to fill the roles assigned to the employers/workforce.
According to Theo Haimann, "Staffing pertains to recruitment, selection, development and compensation of subordinates."
Nature of Staffing FunctionStaffing is an important managerial function- Staffing function is the most important mangerial act along with planning, organizing, directing and controlling. The operations of these four functions depend upon the manpower which is available through staffing function.
Staffing is a pervasive activity- As staffing function is carried out by all managers and in all types of concerns where business activities are carried out.
Staffing is a continuous activity- This is because staffing function continues throughout the life of an organization due to the transfers and promotions that take place.
STAFFING PROCESS - STEPS INVOLVED IN STAFFING
Manpower requirements- The very first step in staffing is to plan the manpower inventory required by a concern in order to match them with the job requirements and demands. Therefore, it involves forecasting and determining the future manpower needs of the concern.
Recruitment- Once the requirements are notified, the concern invites and solicits applications according to the invitations made to the desirable candidates.

Selection- This is the screening step of staffing in which the solicited applications are screened out and suitable candidates are appointed as per the requirements.
Orientation and Placement- Once screening takes place, the appointed candidates are made familiar to the work units and work environment through the orientation programmes. Placement takes place by putting right man on the right job.

Training and Development- Training is a part of incentives given to the workers in order to develop and grow them within the concern. Training is generally given according to the nature of activities and scope of expansion in it. Along with it, the workers are developed by providing them extra benefits of indepth knowledge of their functional areas. Development also includes giving them key and important jobs as a test or examination in order to analyse their performances.
Remuneration- It is a kind of compensation provided monetarily to the employees for their work performances. This is given according to the nature of job- skilled or unskilled, physical or mental, etc. Remuneration forms an important monetary incentive for the employees.
Performance Evaluation- In order to keep a track or record of the behaviour, attitudes as well as opinions of the workers towards their jobs. For this regular assessment is done to evaluate and supervise different work units in a concern. It is basically concerning to know the development cycle and growth patterns of the employees in a concern.
Promotion and transfer- Promotion is said to be a non-monetary incentive in which the worker is shifted from a higher job demanding bigger responsibilities as well as shifting the workers and transferring them to different work units and branches of the same organization.
In field of management, direction is said to be all those activities which are designed to encourage the subordinates to work effectively and efficiently.According to Human, "Directing consists of process or technique by which instruction can be issued and operations can be carried out as originally planned"Therefore, Directing is the function of guiding, inspiring, overseeing and instructing people towards accomplishment of organizational goals.
Directing Function of Management
DIRECTING is said to be a process in which the managers instruct, guide and oversee the performance of the workers to achieve predetermined goals.
Directing is said to be the heart of management process. Planning, organizing, staffing have got no importance if direction function does not take place.
Directing initiates action and it is from here actual work starts. Direction is said to be consisting of human factors. In simple words, it can be described as providing guidance to workers is doing work.
It Initiates Actions - Directions is the function which is the starting point of the work performance of subordinates. It is from this function the action takes place, subordinates understand their jobs and do according to the instructions laid. Whatever are plans laid, can be implemented only once the actual work starts. It is there that direction becomes beneficial.
It Ingrates Efforts - Through direction, the superiors are able to guide, inspire and instruct the subordinates to work. For this, efforts of every individual towards accomplishment of goals are required. It is through direction the efforts of every department can be related and integrated with others. This can be done through persuasive leadership and effective communication. Integration of efforts bring effectiveness and stability in a concern

Importance of Directing Function
Directing or Direction function is said to be the heart of management of process and therefore, is the central point around which accomplishment of goals take place. A few philosophers call Direction as "Life spark of an enterprise". It is also called as on actuating function of management because it is through direction that the operation of an enterprise actually starts. Being the central character of enterprise, it provides many benefits to a concern which are as follows:
Coping up with the changes - It is a human behaviour that human beings show resistance to change. Adaptability with changing environment helps in sustaining planned growth and becoming a market leader. It is directing function which is of use to meet with changes in environment, both internal as external. Effective communication helps in coping up with the changes. It is the role of manager here to communicate the nature and contents of changes very clearly to the subordinates. This helps in clarifications, easy adaptions and smooth running of an enterprise. For example, if a concern shifts from handlooms to powerlooms, an important change in technique of production takes place. The resulting factors are less of manpower and more of machinery. This can be resisted by the subordinates. The manager here can explain that the change was in the benefit of the subordinates. Through more mechanization, production increases and thereby the profits. Indirectly, the subordinates are benefited out of that in form of higher remuneration.
Means of Motivation - Direction function helps in achievement of goals. A manager makes use of the element of motivation here to improve the performances of subordinates. This can be done by providing incentives or compensation, whether monetary or non-monetary, which serves as a "Morale booster" to the subordinates. Motivation is also helpful for the subordinates to give the best of their abilities which ultimately helps in growth.
It Provides Stability - Stability and balance in concern becomes very important for long term sun survival in the market. This can be brought upon by the managers with the help of four tools or elements of direction function - judicious blend of persuasive leadership, effective communication, strict supervision and efficient motivation. Stability is very important since that is an index of growth of an enterprise. Therefore a manager can use of all the four traits in him so that performance standards can be maintained.
Controlling Function of Management
Controlling consists of verifying whether everything occurs in confirmities with the plans adopted, instructions issued and principles established.
Controlling ensures that there is effective and efficient utilization of organizational resources so as to achieve the planned goals.
Controlling measures the deviation of actual performance from the standard performance, discovers the causes of such deviations and helps in taking corrective actions
Features of Controlling FunctionFollowing are the characteristics of controlling function of management-
Controlling is an end function- A function which comes once the performances are made in confirmities with plans.
Controlling is a pervasive function- which means it is performed by managers at all levels and in all type of concerns.
Controlling is forward looking- because effective control is not possible without past being controlled. Controlling always look to future so that follow-up can be made whenever required.
According to Brech, "Controlling is a systematic exercise which is called as a process of checking actual performance against the standards or plans with a view to ensure adequate progress and also recording such experience as is gained as a contribution to possible future needs."
According to Donnell, "Just as a navigator continually takes reading to ensure whether he is relative to a planned action, so should a business manager continually take reading to assure himself that his enterprise is on right course."Controlling has got two basic purposes:
It facilitates co-ordination
It helps in planning

